McWhirter, Mrs. FT mss., 1840-1979 LMC 2183
Lilly Library
McWhirter, Mrs. FT mss.
1840-1979
1953
1954
1958
1960
1961
1963
1964
1971
1974
Lilly Library
LMC 2183
2315 Items 7 boxes; 2 oversize folios
The McWhirter, Mrs. F.T. mss., 1840-1979, are papers of Luella Frances (Smith) McWhirter (Mrs. Felix Tony McWhirter), 1859-1952, clubwoman.
Access Restrictions
This collection is open for research.
Biographical Note
Luella Frances (Smith) McWhirter was born October 1, 1859 at Perrysville, Vermillion County, Indiana, the daughter of the Reverend Hezekiah Smith and Susan Davis (Marsters) Smith. She was educated at East Tennessee Wesleyan College, in Athens, Tennessee, and DePauw University. She married Felix Tony McWhirter, November 18, 1878. Following their marriage they resided in Athens, Tennessee and Greencastle, Indiana, where Mr. McWhirter was member of the English Department of DePauw University. They moved to Indianapolis in 1888. Positions Luella held throughout her career are as follows:
Indiana W.C.T.U. treasurer, 1893-1896, president, 1896-1900, trustee, 1927-1937 and 1940, honorary president, 1940-1952, editor, The Message, official paper of the Indiana W.C.T.U., 1897-1913 and 1919-1945; director, Peoples' State Bank of Indianapolis, 1900-1936; president, Woman's Research Club, 1907-1909; appointed to represent Indiana in Congress of Mothers, Washington, D.C., 1908; president, seventh [Indiana] Federation of Clubs, 1911; Indiana Federation of Clubs, president, 1911-1913, honorary president, 1938-1952, chairman, American Home Department, 1924-1927, organizer, War Victory Commission, 1916-1918; one of organizers, Woman's Franchise League of Indiana, vice-president, 1911; founder, Woman's Department Club of Indianapolis, 1912, president, 1922-1926; General Federation of Women's Clubs, president, State Presidents' Club, 1912, director for Indiana, 1916-1920, transportation chairman, 1916-1924, chairman, War Victory Commission, chairman, Extension Department, 1925-1927, trustee, 1932-1938, chairman, Federation Foundation Fund for six Midwest states; president, Legislative Council of Indiana Women, 1917; vice-president, Indiana Dry Federation, 1917; trustee, 1917-1945, Robert W. Long College for Women (to be established); director, United States Good Roads, 1918-1920; chairman, Indianapolis drive for building funds, Women's Union Christian Colleges in the Orient, 1922; president, Indiana Conference Deaconess Board, Methodist Episcopal Church, 1926-1937; member, President's Conference on Home Building and Home Ownership, 1931-1932; chairman, Woman's Loyalty Committee for Indiana, United Protestant Church Loyalty Crusade, 1932; Indiana White Cross Guild, Methodist Hospital, Indianapolis, president, 1932-1934, president emeritus, 1934-1952; member, Jury of award on Model Homes of Indiana, Federal Housing Administration, 1936; National League of American Pen Women, charter member and vice-president for Indiana branch, 1936-1938; regional mother, Golden Rule Foundation, 1942; trustee, Taylor University; historian, May Wright Sewall State Council of Women; member: Caroline Scott Harrison Chapter of the Daughters of the American Revolution, Society of Indiana Pioneers, Epsilon Sigma Omicron, Central Avenue Methodist Episcopal Church, Indianapolis, Indiana, Association of Parliamentarians, Woman's Press Club of Indiana; died, December 10, 1952.
Biographical accounts of Mrs. McWhirter appear also in Blanche Foster Boruff's Women of Indiana... (Indianapolis, 1941), p. 199 and Mildred Marshall Scouller's Women Who Man Our Clubs... (Philadelphia, 1934), pp. 146-148.
Scope and Content Note
The collection is organized into the following series: I. Subjects; II. Scrapbooks; III. Printed; IV. Photographs; V. Miscellaneous.
The Subjects series contains correspondence, addresses, constitutions and by-laws, minutes of meetings, membership lists, histories of organizations, yearbooks, programs, and publicity materials. They are arranged alphabetically after biographical and genealogical information, and letters of condolence on the death of Mrs. McWhirter.
Correspondents in the Subjects series include: Mildred (Carlson) Ahlgren, Albion (Fellows) Bacon, Bertha (Crosley) Ball, Arcada Campbell (Stark) Balz, Eliza A. (Cooper) Blaker, Ella Alexander Boole, Evangeline Cory Booth, Marie Caroline Brehm, William Lowe Bryan, Mary (Quick) Burnet, Amos William Butler, Nannie C. (Lucas) Canine, Eleanore Elliott Carroll, Grace (Julian) Clarke, Mamie (White) Colvin, Clara Ruth (Meid) Compton, Milton Conover, Sallie (Southall) Cotten, Lucy (Jennings) Dickinson, Nettie A. (Geiger) Downey, Saidie (Orr) Dunbar, Carrie Belle (Tyler) Fenton, Irving Fisher, Gerald Rudolph Ford, James Ford, William Fortune, James Putnam Goodrich, Anna Adams Gordon, John Matthew Gries, Lottie (Lyons) Grow, James Franklin Hanly, Rolla Neil Harger, Ida (Husted) Harper, Mary Garrett Hay, William Harrison Hays, Catharine (Spicer) Hitch, Herbert Hoover, Mary Hannah (Hanchett) Hunt, John Newell Hurty, Allan Jackson, Charles Bacon Jackson, Mrs. Haute (Tarkington) Jameson, Evelyn (Hageman) Jaqua, Rose Carolyn (Byers) Katterhenry, Helen Adams Keller, John Harvy Kellogg, Edward Joseph Kelly, Araminta (Cooper) Kern, Estella M. (Stiles) King, Helen (McCreadie) Knight, Robert Patterson Lamont, Roberta (Campbell) Lawson, Mary Ashton (Rice) Livermore, Katherine (Huber) Ludlow, Louis Leon Ludlow, Warren Terry McCray, Felix Tony McWhirter, Nancy Caroline (Tyree) McWhirter, Shailer Mathews, Mable (Warner) Millikan, James Atwell Mount, Harry Stewart New, Vida Newsom, R. Earl Peters, Grace (Smith) Pettijohn, Amelia Waring Platter, Anne (Carlisle) Porter, Bertha (Kelsey) Poston, Samuel Moffett Ralson, Anna Steese (Sausser) Richardson, Maude Ellen (Lucas) Rumpler, Elizabeth (Gunn) Seebirt, May (Wright) Sewall, Albert Shaw, Margaret (Espy) Vennedge Sheridan, Mary Belle (King) Sherman, Bettie M. Sipple, Hezekiah Smith, Mabel (Johnson) Smith, Rodney Smith, Susan Davis (Marsters) Smith, Elizabeth (Tipton) Stanley, Sara (Messing) Stern, Lillian M. N. (Ames) Stevens, Katharine Adelia (Lente) Stevenson, James Arthur Stuart, Milo H. Stuart, Thomas Taggart, Booth Tarkington, Susan (Davis) Taylor, Elizabeth Ione (McDonald) Thornburgh, M. Clifford Townsend, Phebe (Kerrick) Warner, James Eli Watson, William Allen White, Cora (Young) Wiles, Frances Elizabeth Willard, Vella Alberta Winner, Alice (Ames) Winter, Evans Woollen, William Watson Woollen, John Granville Wooley, and Rose Emmet Young. Consult the Manuscripts Index in the Library for dates and locations of letters of individual correspondents.
Acquisition Information
Gift: 1953, 1954, 1958, 1960, 1961, 1963, 1964, 1971, 1974
McWhirter, Luella Frances (Smith), 1859-1952
- I. Subjects
  - Biographical and genealogical, 1898-1970; 4 Folders (Box 1)
  - Letters of condolence on the death of Mrs. McWhirter, 3 Folders (Box 1)
  - Autographs (Box 1)
  - Badges (Box 1)
  - Better Homes in America: (Box 1)
  - 1924-1942, 5 Folders (Box 1)
  - , publicity notebook, 1933 (Box 1)
  - , newspaper clippings, 1934-1942 (Box 1)
  - Citizens Committee of One Thousand (Box 1)
  - Contests (Box 1)
  - Daughters of the American Revolution, 2 Folders (Box 1)
  - Epsilon Sigma Omicron (Box 1)
  - Federation of Women's Boards of Foreign Missions of North America (Box 1)
  - Ford, Gerald Rudolph (Box 1)
  - General Federation of Women's Clubs: (Box 1)
  - 1912-1929 (Box 1)
  - 1930-1946 (Box 1)
  - Newspaper clippings (Box 1)
  - Federation Foundation fund (Box 1)
  - State President's Club, 1912 (Box 1)
  - Committee on Federation Extension (Box 1)
  - General Federation of Women's Clubs: (Box 2)
  - Transportation Chairman, 1899-1924; 2 Folders (Box 2)
  - World War Service Board (Box 2)
  - Golden Rule Foundation (Box 2)
  - Golden Rule Foundation. American Mother's Committee (Box 2)
  - Hoosier Salon Patron's Association. Hoosier Program Bureau (Box 2)
  - Indiana Association of Parliamentarians (Box 2)
  - Indiana Audubon Society (Box 2)
  - Indiana Dry Federation (Box 2)
  - Indiana Federation of Clubs: (Box 2)
  - 1909-1956, 6 Folders (Box 2)
  - Newspaper clippings (Box 2)
  - Department of the American Home, 1923-1941; 3 Folders (Box 2)
  - Department of the American Home, newspaper clippings (Box 2)
  - War Victory Commission, 1916-1918 (Box 2)
  - Indiana School of Religion (Box 2)
  - Indianapolis, IN, Methodist Hospital (Box 2)
  - Jacob E. Wile Memorial Nurses Home (Box 2)
  - White Cross Guild (Box 2)
  - White Cross Guild, newspaper clippings (Box 2)
  - Indianapolis Local Council of Women (Box 2)
  - International Council of Women (Box 2)
  - Invitations (Box 2)
  - Legislative Council of Indiana Women (Box 2)
  - McWhirter, Felix Tony: (Box 2)
  - Condolences on death of (Box 2)
  - To McWhirter, Mrs. Luella Frances (Smith) (Box 2)
  - McWhirter, Luella Frances(Smith). Addresses, 1896-1937, 2 Folders (Box 2)
  - McWhirter, Luella Frances (Smith): (Box 3)
  - Diaries:, 1884; 1927 (Box 3)
  - Diary sheets, 1894-1941 (Box 3)
  - Methodist Episcopal Church: (Box 3)
  - Indiana State Council (Box 3)
  - Women's Foreign Missionary Society (Box 3)
  - Women's Home Missionary Society. Deaconess Home. Indiana conference (Box 3)
  - Minerva Club, Indianapolis (Box 3)
  - Miscellaneous letters and papers:, 1873-1961; 7 Folders (Box 3)
  - Printed material (Box 3)
  - Newspaper clippings (Box 3)
  - Missions (Box 3)
  - National Congress of Parents and Teachers (Box 3)
  - National Federation of Business and Professional Women's Clubs (Box 3)
  - National League of American Pen Women. Indiana branch (Box 3)
  - National Prohibition Emergency Committee (Box 3)
  - Near East relief (Box 3)
  - Peoples State Bank, Indianapolis (Box 3)
  - Perugia. Regia universita italiana per stranieri (Box 3)
  - Photographs. Obituaries and remembrances of Luella Frances (Smith) McWhirter, 1952 (Box 3)
  - President's Conference on Home Building and Home Ownership, Washington, D.C., 1930-1933; 2 Folders (Box 3)
  - Prohibition (Box 3)
  - Scoggins, Ethel (McWhirter). Includes:Ethel McWhirter Scoggins: An Autobiography (Box 3)
  - Society of Indiana Pioneers (Box 3)
  - Southern Commercial Congress (Box 3)
  - United Protestant Church Loyalty Crusade (Box 3)
  - United States Good Roads Association, Inc. (Box 3)
  - U.S. Federal Housing Administration (Box 3)
  - Vellore, India. Missionary Medical College For Women (Box 3)
  - Women's Christian Temperance Union: (Box 4)
  - 1879-1950, 11 Folders (Box 4)
  - Publicity department (Box 4)
  - Woman's Department Club, Indianapolis:, 1912-1954; 5 Folders (Box 4)
  - American Home Club Institute, 1926 (Box 4)
  - Newspaper clippings (Box 4)
  - Yearbooks, 1912-1915; 1937-1956; 1963-1965; 1968-1971; 1972-1975; 1976-1979; 32 Volumes (Box 4)
  - Woman's National Committee for Law Enforcement (Box 5)
  - Woman's Press Club of Indiana (Box 5)
  - Woman's Research Club, Indianapolis, Ind. (Box 5)
  - Women's Suffrage (Box 5)
  - Women's Union Christian Colleges in the Orient (Box 5)
  - YWCA (Box 5)
- II. Scrapbooks
  - 1. Miscellaneous scrapbooks:, 1875-1939; 1895-1919; 1916-1929; 1921-1932; 1930-1939 (Box 5)
  - 2. Armenian pageant, war victory, dry federation, etc., 2 Folders (Box 5)
  - 3. Badges, 1893-1938 (Box 5)
  - 4. Better homes, 1926-1935 (Box 5)
  - 5. Henry Long College for Women, Oriental colleges, Hoosier Program Bureau and legislative acts, etc., 2 Folders (Box 5)
  - 6. Indiana Federation of Clubs, 1909-1938; 3 Folders (Box 6)
  - 7. Letterheads (Box 6)
  - 8. Woman's Department Club: (early history), 1912-1924; 1922-1925; 1925-1926; 1926-1937 (Box 6)
  - 9. Women's suffrage, 1913-1920 (Box 6)
  - 10. W.T.C.U.:, 1888-1936; 1932-1933 (Box 6)
  - 11. Undated bound scrapbook (Box 6)
- III. Printed
  - The Message (W.T.C.U.), 1916, Jan.-1939, Dec.; 3 Folders (Box 6)
  - The Message (W.T.C.U.), 1940-1949; 3 Folders (Box 6)
  - Indiana Club Woman, 1927-1941; 1943-1947 (Box 6)
  - A 30-year History of the Indiana Federation of Clubs, 1938-1968 (Box 6)
  - Year Book of the Society of Indiana Pioneers, 1971 (Box 6)
  - History Indiana Federation of Clubs (Box 6)
  - Indianapolis Blue Book:, 1925; 1929 (Box 6)
  - Famous Living Americans (Box 6)
  - Women of Indiana (Box 6)
  - Women's Press Club of Indiana. Newspaper clipping, 1913 (Box 6)
  - The Indianapolis Sunday Star, part five, Vol. 35, No. 169. Features articles on the Indiana federation of clubs, November 21, 1937 (Oversize [1])
  - The Message - Supplement. Reprint of letter by Mrs. McWhirter, vol. III, no. 5., May 1899 (Oversize [2])
  - The Organizer, [Vol. I?, no. 1?], undated and Vol. I, no. 2. Semi-monthly publication of the Woman's National Christian Temperance Union, November 1, 1882 (Oversize [3])
  - The Union Signal, Vol. XXIV, no. 10. W.C.T.U. publication, March 10, 1898 (Oversize [4])
  - Miscellaneous clippings (Oversize [5])
- IV. Photographs
  - . Hezekiah Smith, Susan Smith, Smith family (5 photographs), 1840-1870 (Box 7)
  - . Luella Smith (7 photographs), 1864-1876 (Box 7)
  - . Felix McWhirter (2 photographs), 1875-1910 (Box 7)
  - . Luella Smith with others (3 photographs), 1870s (Box 7)
  - . Indiana Ashbury University, 1881 (Box 7)
  - . Luella McWhirter Hutchins (2 photographs), 1888-1890 (Box 7)
  - . Luella Smith McWhirter (2 photographs), 1890 (Box 7)
  - . W.C.T.U. Assembly, Bay City, MI (2 photographs), 1895 (Box 7)
  - ,. W.C.T.U. Assemblies, WA and IN (2 photographs), 1896; 1900 (Box 7)
  - . Luella Smith McWhirter (7 photographs), 1897-1913 (Box 7)
  - . Luella Smith McWhirter (8 photographs), 1904-1912 (Box 7)
  - ca.. Luella Smith McWhirter with other club members (2 folders), 1912 (Box 7)
  - . W.C.T.U. and other banquets (5 photographs), 1916-1919 (Box 7)
  - . Peoples State Bank, Indianapolis, IN (12 photographs), 1918-1972 (Box 7)
  - . State School for the Deaf luncheon, 1920 (Box 7)
  - . Luella Smith McWhirter and grandchildren, 1923 (Box 7)
  - ,. Woman's Department Club (3 photographs), 1924; 1931 (Box 7)
  - . W.C.T.U. members. American Mission College for Girls, Cairo, Egypt (8 photographs), 1926 (Box 7)
  - . Mediterranean cruise, incl. Jerusalem, Algiers, Egypt (7 photographs), 1926-1927 (Box 7)
  - . W.C.T.U. Lausanne, Switzerland (5 photographs), 1928 (Box 7)
  - Undated. Steven Marsters (2 photographs) (Box 7)
  - Undated. W.C.T.U. leaders and members (5 photographs) (Box 7)
  - Undated. Miscellaneous (3 photographs) (Box 7)
  - Glass transparency: McWhirter, Luella Smith (Box 7)
  - Tintypes: (Box 7)
  - Marsters, Rev. Stephen, Jr. (Box 7)
  - Smith, Rev. and Mrs. Hezekiah & Luella (Box 7)
  - Smith, Captain Mark (Box 7)
  - Smith, Peter (Box 7)
  - . National W.C.T.U. convention, dinner in Riley Room of Claypool Hotel, Indianapolis, 1918 (Oversize [6])
  - . Mrs. McWhirter at the State House, 1920 (Oversize [7])
  - . Group photograph at State House, 1920 (Oversize [8])
  - . Indiana Women at Chautauqua, New York, 1920 (Oversize [9])
  - . Biannual conference of the General Federation of Women Clubs held at Armory, Grand Rapids, Michigan, 1927; May 31 to June 4, 1927 (Oversize [10])
  - ca.. Indiana convention W.C.T.U., at Trinity M.E. Church, Elkhart, Indiana, 1930; Oct. 7-10 (Oversize [11])
  - . Indiana Federation of Clubs, Riley Room, Claypool Hotel, 1932; Nov. 1-3 (Oversize [12])
  - . White House reception by President Hoover, General Federation of Women's Clubs, 1933, Jan. 11 (Oversize [13])
- V. Miscellaneous
  - Presentation trowel from Indiana Industrial School, April 8, 1898 (Box 7)
  - Pi Gamma Mu. Certificate; enrollment card, undated., Mar. 15, 1929 (Oversize [14])
  - Daughters of the American Revolution. Certificate, Mar. 7, 1911 (Oversize [15])
  - Broadside. To "Club Sisters" from Mrs. McWhirter, Indiana Federation of Clubs, War Victory Commission. Concerning furlough houses during WWI (Oversize [16])
  - Poster: "The Great Day!...at Bethany Park, Monday." Featured speakers: Mrs. McWhirter, A.L. Crim (candidate for Secretary of State) and Professor J.E. Hawes (evangelist), July 22, 1906 (Oversize [17])
  - Poster: "An Up-To-Date 4th of July Picnic." Undated. Featured speakers: Mrs. McWhirter and Rev. E.G. Shouse of Kokomo (Oversize [18])